<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Judaism for Gentiles on Evelyn Park</title>
    <link>https://evelynpark.com/series/judaism-for-gentiles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Judaism for Gentiles on Evelyn Park</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.3</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>CC BY Evelyn Park · Privacy Policy</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://evelynpark.com/series/judaism-for-gentiles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles: Lecture 1</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first lecture was given on the morning of August 3, 2025. The video is available to stream &lt;del&gt;and to download&lt;/del&gt;. You can also download &lt;del&gt;just the audio&lt;/del&gt;, subtitles, or transcripts in a variety of formats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit: Due to technical limitations, I am unable to provide large file downloads at this time. I hope to resolve this soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still rendering&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;audio&#34;&gt;Audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;ogg&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;transcript&#34;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1.srt&#34;&gt;srt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1.tsv&#34;&gt;tsv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1.txt&#34;&gt;txt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1.vtt&#34;&gt;vtt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 3: Did &#34;The Jews&#34; Kill Jesus?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/did-jews-kill-jesus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/did-jews-kill-jesus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, there is no consensus over whether Jesus was a real historical figure. For the sake of answering this question, we will treat the Gospel narratives as being more or less reliable historical accounts, and analyze it in light of contemporary political forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rapid-fire-recap-second-temple-politics&#34;&gt;Rapid Fire Recap: Second Temple Politics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire region was hotly contested because of its militarily and economically valuable location. The current regime, the Hasmonean Dynasty, came to power after a successful rebellion against the Hellenistic successors of Alexander the Great, and promptly made Judea into a Roman vassal state. Contemporary politics featured three major factions: the Pharisees, who emphasized obedience to the Law and personal responsibility; the Sadducees, who emphasized the Temple cult and engaged in politics to protect the interests of the Hasmonean priesthood; and the Zealots, who were guerilla military bands seeking independence from Rome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 2: What Did Jesus Think About Judaism?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-did-jesus-think-about-judaism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-did-jesus-think-about-judaism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;historical-background&#34;&gt;Historical Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus&amp;rsquo;s day, Judaism was in a time of significant change and upheaval. Second Temple religion and politics were a struggle between three major factions. The Sadducees represented the priestly Temple cult; the Pharisees advocated for a legalistic or scribal cult born in the Babylonian exile; and the Zealots were a military faction intent on Judean independence from Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-maccabees&#34;&gt;The Maccabees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judea&amp;rsquo;s location on the Mediterranean coast and between Egypt and Asia Minor make it militarily and economically valuable. Following the death of Alexander the Great, his successors competed for control of the region. The various ruling classes of Judea invariably sided with different Hellenistic factions, seeing political and economic advantages. As a result, Hellenism became increasingly appealing to Judean aristocrats. Greek replaced Hebrew, kosher laws were ignored, a hymnasium was built in which Jews competed in Hellenistic athletic games nude, and circumcisions were either not performed or reversed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 1: What Do Jews Think About Jesus?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-do-jews-think-about-jesus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-do-jews-think-about-jesus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-jews-think-about-jesus&#34;&gt;What Do Jews Think about Jesus?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-historical-jesus&#34;&gt;The Historical Jesus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A prerequisite question to consider is whether Jesus existed as a legitimate historical figure. Christians answer this question in a variety of ways, with more conservative or fundamentalist sects asserting definitively that, yes, Jesus was a real historical figure, and more liberal sects being more open to the possibility that he may not have been. Modern historical scholarship tends to side with the latter opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
