<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Evelyn Park</title>
    <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Evelyn Park</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://evelynpark.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles: Lecture 4</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cj5AGoqAl74?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles: Lecture 3</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/q0p0Whwe0A8?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles: Lecture 2</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MG94jt02U2U?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 5: Jewish Holidays</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/jewish-holidays/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/jewish-holidays/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-holidays&#34;&gt;High Holidays&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;rosh-hoshanah&#34;&gt;Rosh Hoshanah&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rosh Hoshanah is the Jewish New Year, and is the beginning of a roughly week-long period of repentance, reflection, and remembrance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rosh Hoshanah is primarily associated with the mitzvah of hearing the blowing of the shofar, a ram&amp;rsquo;s horn which is blown on certain ritual occasions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;yom-kippur&#34;&gt;Yom Kippur&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yom Kippur, the Day of Atonement, takes place 9 days after Rosh Hoshanah.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yom Kippur is characterized by the strictest restrictions of any day in the Jewish year. In addition to the work-related restrictions of Shabbat, Yom Kippur prohibits bathing, anointing with oil or perfume, engaging in sexual relations, and wearing leather shoes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 4: Visual Aids</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-visual-aids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-visual-aids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After hearing some feedback on the first lecture, I realized that I may have put the cart in the gift horse&amp;rsquo;s mouth. In order to provide context for the topics discussed both previously and going forward, I&amp;rsquo;ve put together some visuals. One is a chart which explains the Tanakh, the order of its books, and how they are divided. Next is a couple of brief timelines which should help place events in relative context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles: Lecture 1</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/judaism-for-gentiles-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;&#xA;      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/11b6-_6Zswg?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 3: Did &#34;The Jews&#34; Kill Jesus?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/did-jews-kill-jesus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/did-jews-kill-jesus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, there is no consensus over whether Jesus was a real historical figure. For the sake of answering this question, we will treat the Gospel narratives as being more or less reliable historical accounts, and analyze it in light of contemporary political forces.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;rapid-fire-recap-second-temple-politics&#34;&gt;Rapid Fire Recap: Second Temple Politics&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The entire region was hotly contested because of its militarily and economically valuable location. The current regime, the Hasmonean Dynasty, came to power after a successful rebellion against the Hellenistic successors of Alexander the Great, and promptly made Judea into a Roman vassal state. Contemporary politics featured three major factions: the Pharisees, who emphasized obedience to the Law and personal responsibility; the Sadducees, who emphasized the Temple cult and engaged in politics to protect the interests of the Hasmonean priesthood; and the Zealots, who were guerilla military bands seeking independence from Rome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 2: What Did Jesus Think About Judaism?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-did-jesus-think-about-judaism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-did-jesus-think-about-judaism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;historical-background&#34;&gt;Historical Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Jesus&amp;rsquo;s day, Judaism was in a time of significant change and upheaval. Second Temple religion and politics were a struggle between three major factions. The Sadducees represented the priestly Temple cult; the Pharisees advocated for a legalistic or scribal cult born in the Babylonian exile; and the Zealots were a military faction intent on Judean independence from Rome.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-maccabees&#34;&gt;The Maccabees&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Judea&amp;rsquo;s location on the Mediterranean coast and between Egypt and Asia Minor make it militarily and economically valuable. Following the death of Alexander the Great, his successors competed for control of the region. The various ruling classes of Judea invariably sided with different Hellenistic factions, seeing political and economic advantages. As a result, Hellenism became increasingly appealing to Judean aristocrats. Greek replaced Hebrew, kosher laws were ignored, a hymnasium was built in which Jews competed in Hellenistic athletic games nude, and circumcisions were either not performed or reversed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Books on Judaism</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/reading-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:42:28 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/reading-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cahill, T. (2010). The Gifts of the Jews: How a Tribe of Desert Nomads Changed the Way Everyone Thinks and Feels. Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Semi-historical work about the contribution of Jews to Western culture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Donin, H. (2019). To be a Jew: A Guide to Jewish Observance in Contemporary Life Selected and Compiled from the Shulhan Arukh and Responsa Literature and Providing a Rationale for the Laws and the Traditions. Basic Books.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Foundational textbook to practical, everyday halacha.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fox, E. (1997). The Five Books of Moses: Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, Deuteronomy. Schocken Books.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;My favorite Torah translation. Bad English, but very good Hebrew-in-English, preserving many Hebrew puns and poetic forms which other translations tend to lose or interpret away.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gans, C. (2016). A Political Theory for the Jewish People: Three Zionist Narratives. Oxford University Press.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Comprehensive review of various strands of Zionist thought and Levantine politics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Green, A. (2012). These Are the Words: A Vocabulary of Jewish Spiritual Life. Jewish Lights Pub.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A short dictionary explaining common Jewish words.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hayes, C. E. (2012). Introduction to the Bible. Yale University Press.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Excellent, digestible introduction to modern Hebrew Bible scholarship.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Heschel, A. J. (1999). God in Search of Man: A Philosophy of Judaism. Farrar, Straus and Giroux.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A comprehensive philosophy of Judaism as a religion of awe.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Heschel, A. J. (2005). The Sabbath: Its Meaning for Modern Man. Farrar, Straus and Giroux.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A short and beautiful text about the importance and meaning of Shabbat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hurwitz, S. (2019). Here All Along: Finding Meaning, Spirituality, and a Deeper Connection to Life in Judaism (After Finally Choosing to Look There). Spiegel &amp;amp; Grau.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A brief exploration of the often-overlooked spiritual aspect of Judaism.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kushner, A. (2015). The Grammar of God: A Journey into the Words and Worlds of the Bible. Spiegel &amp;amp; Grau.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A brief exploration of the role of Hebrew grammar in Biblical analysis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shṭainzalts, ʿAdin. (2002). A Guide to Jewish Prayer. Schocken Books.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Foundational textbook to practical Jewish prayer.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;revision-history&#34;&gt;Revision History&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2025-06-28: Original posting.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tale of Two Sonics</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/tale-of-two-sonics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 16:48:14 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/tale-of-two-sonics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;icecream.gif&#34; alt=&#34;A gif of a kid&amp;rsquo;s ice cream flying sideways off the cone for no reason.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I saw the first Sonic movie, it was out of morbid curiosity. Surely there was no way the studio could have salvaged what was sure to be a trainwreck, another cash-grab live action film preying on nostalgia with no meaningful substance to speak of.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Boy, was I wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first movie wasn&amp;rsquo;t perfect. It had a few too many dated jokes and Fortnite dances. It was a little generic. But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t remotely &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;. It was, in fact, a somewhat touching tale about a blue alien finding a family in a faraway land, and learning to stop running (lol) and stand up to protect what was important to him. Classic shonen manga stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judaism for Gentiles 1: What Do Jews Think About Jesus?</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-do-jews-think-about-jesus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/what-do-jews-think-about-jesus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-jews-think-about-jesus&#34;&gt;What Do Jews Think about Jesus?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-historical-jesus&#34;&gt;The Historical Jesus&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A prerequisite question to consider is whether Jesus existed as a legitimate historical figure. Christians answer this question in a variety of ways, with more conservative or fundamentalist sects asserting definitively that, yes, Jesus was a real historical figure, and more liberal sects being more open to the possibility that he may not have been. Modern historical scholarship tends to side with the latter opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Historicity of the Edict of Cyrus</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/cyrus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 14:16:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/cyrus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt; Was the Edict of Cyrus a true historical event or a Biblical story? From what I can find, arguments on either side of that question are mostly propaganda in support of a political agenda for or against Zionism and claims of Jewish indigeneity to the Levant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In answering this question, it seems to make sense to approach its various parts chronologically, so this essay will begin with a whirlwind overview of the evidence of Israelite-Judean presence in the Levant, then cover evidence for the historicity of the Edict of Cyrus, and finally briefly-but-not-really-at-all touch on claims of indigeneity and modern political philosophy as it applies to the modern state of Israel. Please feel free to skip around.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horse, hevel, and healing</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/horse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 15:40:10 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/horse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This essay hopes to establish the psychopompic fuction of Horse, the enigmatic homeless man in the 2019 Netflix series &lt;em&gt;Russian Doll&lt;/em&gt;. This essay treats the first season as a self-contained standalone story.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-a-psychopomp&#34;&gt;What Is a Psychopomp?&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;psychopomp&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;plural&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;psychopomps&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(&lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt;) A spirit, deity, person, etc., who guides the souls of the dead to the afterlife. (Wiktionary, 2024)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/psychopomp&#34;&gt;Wiktionary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A psychopomp ferries the souls of the dead from this world to the next. The Egyptian Anubis, the Germanic Wotan/Woden/Odin, and our own Grim Reaper — death itself personified — fulfill this psychopompic function.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthopraxy, ethno-religions, and Jewish identity</title>
      <link>https://evelynpark.com/posts/orthopraxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 15:48:04 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evelynpark.com/posts/orthopraxy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nicea-canonization-and-the-aryan-heresy&#34;&gt;Nicea, canonization, and the Aryan Heresy&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the middle of the 4th Century CE, in bustling Alexandria, Egypt, a presbyter name Arius argued that Jesus Christ was a &amp;ldquo;god from nothing&amp;rdquo;. He believed that Jesus was created &lt;em&gt;ex nihilo&lt;/em&gt;, from nothing, the same way that the rest of Creation was. While he may have believed Jesus was the Son of God, and was divine himself, he was not himself God, or made up of the same substance as God.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
