Okay, so, Gary asked the first question, what is a Gentile? A Gentile is just a non-Jew.
So this is Judaism for not Jews. This is class number one. Was it Gary who asked me this morning about, I'm not trying to convert you?
Right. It's just part of your religion to come out in the public and try to educate people.
We don't convert people. We do not do proselytization. The only reason I'm doing this is because around Easter time,
we did that Passover potluck, and people seemed to have some interest in the concept of a Seder and, like, what do Jews do around this time?
And then people brought bread and macaroni and pizza to the Passover potluck, and Passover is the festival of unleavened bread,
and Jews are not allowed to eat bread or pasta or pizza. So I thought that was a little bit, um, almost like a faux pas, kind of, you know?
But, of course, y'all didn't know what Passover was or anything, so that's why I'm doing this class.
If anyone has questions about anything at any point, stop me and ask them.
These are some of the questions that I'm hoping to answer today.
So isn't Judaism just Christianity without Jesus? What's the difference? Like, isn't the only real difference that Jews reject Christ?
Isn't it just Christianity with more rules? Like, what you can and can't do? Like, eat bread during Passover.
And what's the deal with the Jews crucifying our Lord and Savior?
Right, so to answer the Jesus questions, we should probably start with addressing whether or not Jesus was a real history guy,
or just made up, I guess.
Um, so this is a quote from the book, New Testament History and Literature.
The New Testament contains contradictory historical accounts of various parts of early Christianity.
The account of the birth of Jesus and the origins of his family provided by Matthew
is totally different from that in Luke,
and any harmonization cannot stand up to the standards of modern historiography.
The different narratives of his resurrection appearances,
who of his disciples claimed they had seen him, when and where,
and Mark, Matthew, Luke, and Paul all contradict one another.
The New Testament is simply not a reliable source for the history of Jesus or early Christianity
when taken at face value.
This is a pretty common thing for ancient historical sources.
They weren't interested in hard facts the same way that we are.
They were more interested in presenting an interpretation of history in order to convey the right message.
So if a kid asks you, what's electricity?
How does electricity work?
You might answer them, um, well, you know, there's, there's power in the walls,
and the power goes through wires, and it makes machines work,
because kids aren't going to understand electricity is the flow of electrons,
and, uh, electrons flow from a higher to a lower voltage in order to reach equilibrium,
and all that nonsense, and probably most of us don't really understand how electricity works either.
So we present an interpretation of the facts in order to get a message across,
and that is probably what the gospel authors were doing.
And that's why there are some contradictions between accounts.
Well, isn't it also because it was probably oral history and so forth?
I mean, my brother and sister and I can get together and talk about something that happened 40 years ago.
That too, it does.
It doesn't mean a different memory.
So it could be partly.
Yeah, the Bible is probably part of it.
It's not univocal.
It's told by many voices.
And so there's always going to be some differences in how people remember things,
how people choose to tell a story.
But yeah, that does make it a little bit more difficult to nail down the historicity of the gospel accounts.
Okay, so what archaeological evidence do we have for the existence of Jesus as a historical figure?
This is the first pretty much not-gospel evidence that we have for Jesus.
It's called the Alex Aminos graffiti, and scholars date it to around 200 CE.
I am sure that you cannot make out any of this.
So, here's a sketch instead.
We have a horse-headed man hanging on the cross with the inscription,
Alex Aminos worships his God.
This is a sort of derogatory graffiti making fun of this Christian for worshiping a God
who was executed in a brutal and humiliating way.
So, where was it found?
Somewhere in the Roman Empire, but I believe the city of Rome itself.
It's interesting that that's a Roman cross.
It's not the cross that we have.
It's a T-shaped cross.
Yep.
So, we know for sure that by 200 CE, there were some people going around worshiping a God
who had been executed on a cross.
They didn't give us a name or anything for this God, unfortunately,
but we can be pretty sure that it's Jesus.
We also have some non-Christian literary sources from the Jews in the Talmud.
What is the Talmud?
Who knows?
What's the Talmud?
You don't know.
We're all in trouble.
Is it an idol?
Right?
Not really.
Is it a group of people?
Are there the writings?
Is the Talmud the writings?
You have the prophets.
Okay, so you're getting at something sort of different.
So, the Hebrew scriptures or the Old Testament is divided into three sections.
The law, the prophets, and the writings.
The law or the Torah is the first five books.
The five books of Moses or the Pentateuch.
Then you have the prophets, the Nevi'im, we call them in Hebrew.
And that's Isaiah and all those guys.
And we have the writings, the Ketuvim.
That's everything else.
So, the Psalms, Song of Songs, Proverbs, Job, Ecclesiastes, all that stuff.
But that's all in the Hebrew Bible or the Old Testament.
Which we call the Tanakh, which is an acronym.
Torah, Nevi'im, Ketuvim.
After the Tanakh was sort of formalized, Jews kept on saying things and writing things.
And we collected that into a volume called the Mishnah.
And then they kept on saying things and commenting on the Mishnah.
So, we compiled that into the Gemara, which is the commentary on the Mishnah.
And the Mishnah and the Gemara together are called the Talmud.
So, this was probably written down sometime after the Jews were kicked out of Israel the last time.
So, before Moses separated the Red Sea?
Long, long after.
Okay.
Moses was, if he existed, probably a couple thousand years BCE.
And this probably would have been around, I don't know, 200 or so CE.
Around the same time that the New Testament Gospels were being written down, we were writing down the Talmud.
And so, that's just everybody's conversations and commentary on everybody else's conversations.
It's commentaries on commentaries on commentaries.
So, that's why the saying, like, you know, nine Jewish rabbis in a room, ten opinions.
Yeah, two Jews, three opinions.
There's actually a funny story.
The Old Testament translation that Jesus had was called the Septuagint.
It was a translation of the Hebrew into Aramaic, which was kind of the lingua franca of the time.
All the Greeks, the Greek Jews spoke Aramaic.
And it was considered at the time to be a miracle.
Because the Greek authorities got, like, 70 rabbis in a room together.
No, they got, they put 70 rabbis in 70 different rooms.
And they weren't allowed to communicate.
And they all came up with the same Aramaic translation.
But the Jews said, if you want a real miracle, put them all in the same room.
So, this is a story from the Talmud that might be talking about Jesus of Nazareth.
And it goes like, so.
So, on Passover Eve, they hung the corpse of Jesus the Nazarene after they killed him by way of stoning.
And a crier went out before him for 40 days, publicly proclaiming,
Jesus the Nazarene is going to be stoned because he practiced sorcery,
incited people to idol worship, and led the Jewish people astray.
Anyone who knows of a reason to acquit him should come forward and teach it on his behalf.
And the court did not find a reason to acquit him.
And so they stoned him and hung his corpse on Passover Eve.
Ola said, how can you understand this proof?
Was Jesus the Nazarene worthy of conducting a search for a reason to acquit him?
He was an insider to idol worship.
And the merciful one states with regard to an insider to idol worship,
neither shall you spare, neither shall you conceal him.
Rather, Jesus was different as he had close ties with the government
and the Gentile authorities were interested in his acquittal.
So, consequently, the court gave him every opportunity to clear himself
so that it could not be claimed that he was falsely convicted.
What the heck is going on here?
So this story is really about, um, stay,
about due process in Jewish law.
There is this guy called Jesus the Nazarene,
and the Jews are going to execute him for practicing sorcery
and inciting the Jews to idol worship.
And it describes a sort of due process
that the Jews give to Jesus the Nazarene
where they have a guy go out and say,
hey, this guy is on trial.
He's about to be executed.
Anyone who has evidence to help him
should definitely come forward before he dies.
And this rabbi, Ulla, is saying,
why did we do this?
Insiders to idol worship are not supposed to get any sort of due process.
We're supposed to just kill them according to our law.
So what's the deal?
And the answer is,
Jesus was very close to the Gentile authorities,
the Roman government.
So if we just killed him,
that would look bad for us,
and we might get in trouble with the Romans.
So that's why we had a crier go out ahead of time.
This does not sound like the gospel accounts of the crucifixion.
No.
I mean, the Jews hang him on Passover Eve.
That doesn't make any sense
because Jesus was crucified after Passover.
Jesus was not that close to the Gentile authorities,
considering...
They didn't like him.
They kneeled him to a cross, etc., etc.
So, what do we do with this?
Is this evidence of Jesus or not?
We don't know.
Here's another Talmudic story about someone named Jesus.
What is the word on top?
This is the book of the Talmud that it comes from,
and this is the page that it's on.
So, it's kind of like Matthew 7, 9, something like that.
Was Sanhedrin a person?
The Sanhedrin is the Jewish court,
so this is the volume of the Talmud
that deals with the discussions upon discussions
about the Jewish court,
and most of it has nothing to do with the Sanhedrin, actually.
But that's a story for another time.
Yehoshua ben Prechaia said,
How beautiful is this inn?
Jesus, his students, said to him,
But my teacher, the eyes of the innkeeper's wife are narrow.
Yehoshua said to him,
Look in one!
Do not involve yourself with regard to that manner,
the appearance of a married woman.
So he produced 400 shoferot and ostracized him.
So these guys, Yehoshua and his student Jesus,
go to an inn.
Yehoshua says, This inn is awesome.
And Jesus says,
Yeah, and the innkeeper's wife is kind of a looker, right?
That's what eyes are narrow means?
Yeah, she looks like a bit of a loose woman.
I'm like, my eyes are narrow.
So Yehoshua says,
What are you doing commenting on the appearance of a married woman?
Get out of here, you're ostracized.
We shun you.
What's 400 shofar?
A shofar is the horn that we blow at certain ritual occasions.
So he gets 400 people who blow shofar to officially ostracize him from the Jewish community.
And everybody knows it because we had 400 shofar out.
So he's kicked out.
He's pretty much kicked out for this.
Excluded from the community.
So maybe we should just say that Jesus is a very common name.
That is true.
This could be anybody's guess who this person is.
Jesus came before Yehoshua several times and said to him,
Accept my repentance.
Yehoshua took no notice of him.
One day Yehoshua was reciting the Shema, the central prayer in Judaism, one of them.
And Jesus came before him with the same request.
Yehoshua intended to accept his request and signaled him with his hand to wait until he completed his prayer.
It's against Jewish law to interrupt the Shema.
Because it's very important.
So Jesus approaches him while he's reciting and he says,
Hold on a second.
But Jesus didn't understand the signal and thought,
He's driving me away.
So he went and stood a brick upright to serve as an idol and bowed down to it.
Yehoshua then said to Jesus,
Repent!
And Jesus said to him,
This is the tradition that I received from you.
Whoever sins and causes the masses to sin is not given the opportunity to repent.
And the master says,
Jesus performed sorcery inside of the Jews to engage in blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Jews today use this story as an example of how not to treat people.
Often we will say that this was Jesus, Jesus.
Even if the facts don't quite line up.
And we'll say that Jesus went off and started his own religion because one of our rabbis was a jerk and wouldn't take his repentance.
And that's what Jesus says here when he says,
Yehoshua says repent, and Jesus says,
Look, I learned from you that even if I try to repent, you're not going to accept it.
So why should I even bother with you anymore?
You're a jerk.
But is this the Jesus of the New Testament?
I don't know.
So, Evelyn, in this prayer that you just said,
they say, Lord.
Who is the Lord that they're talking about?
The word there in the Hebrew is the Tetragrammaton,
Yad-Heh-Vav-Heh.
This is the name that God gave to Moses at the burning bush to identify himself.
But we don't say that name, so we use a substitution, Adonai, and that's generally translated as Lord.
So, in the Jewish religion, we believe in God, but not Jesus, as our Savior.
That's pretty much what we're trying to answer.
We don't accept him as the Messiah,
but we're also not really sure if he was even a real historical guy
or if the Gospel accounts happened as they're written or, you know.
And why do we not accept Jesus?
What do we really think about him?
Well, to answer that, I will pose to you a question.
Who do you prefer, Rabbi Hillel or Rabbi Shammai?
Don't know the dude.
Yeah, you don't know the dude.
We don't really think about Jesus that much, honestly.
I think there's a sort of misconception that Jews just really are against Jesus,
but kind of just don't care.
I personally think that Jesus, as he's presented in the Gospels,
was a brilliant, radical reformer,
and that the Jews could probably listen to him here and there.
But the whole, like, Messiah, Son of God thing,
it's a little bit odd.
So Jews don't believe in the Holy Trinity.
Where does the Holy Spirit come in here?
The Holy Spirit.
I mean, everybody has the breath of God within them.
Are you going to, at some point,
because I don't want to get in the way of your narrative,
but are you going to talk about some of the differences,
like the differences in terms of belief in an eternal life,
or that sort of thing?
Was I going to?
Maybe, maybe not.
Write it down, add it to your list.
So it's Hillel and Shammai.
You don't know who they are?
Why do you care?
Yeah.
Hillel founded a society.
The Hillel Society.
I don't think he founded that.
He did invent the sandwich, allegedly.
I do want to address this question, though.
Differences in belief like the afterlife and such.
Afterlife is a tricky question,
because it's not directly addressed in the Tanakh,
the Hebrew scriptures.
So in the Tanakh,
the closest that we get to is a place called Sheol.
Translates to grave,
described as a dark, watery place underground.
So according to the Tanakh,
when you die, you get buried.
And that's about as far as we get.
After the Tanakh,
we have come up with various different theories.
One of them is the idea of the world to come.
This is pretty analogous to what Jesus would have called
the kingdom of God.
Some sort of utopian future
in which things will not suck.
And maybe some of us will come back to life.
Maybe some of us won't.
Some people believed in the resurrection.
Some didn't.
The Apostle Paul actually manages to escape
from persecution once
by bringing up bodily resurrection.
And then all the Jews start arguing with each other
and he kind of just slips away.
Some Jews today believe in reincarnation.
There's no real agreement.
Who were these people?
Hillel and Shammai were two very popular rabbis
back in the day.
What did it?
I don't know.
Nobody knows the mythical time of
when we tell stories about the sages.
No one knows.
But they, yes?
The question is,
the Gospels were written like,
say, a hundred years or so
after the death of Jesus.
Yes.
Now, when was this written and stuff?
I mean, is everything just open to interpretations
from who's ever writing whatever, you know?
The Talmud was probably written
about the same time as the Gospels.
So everything takes place
hundreds of years after the fact.
So it's just whatever the people,
you know,
oh, well, so-and-so said this or that.
And they don't actually know.
I mean.
Whatever message that they're trying to get across
is what they write down.
They didn't have cell phones to them.
And the internet.
And most people were not very literate,
so they couldn't have written things down.
Right.
We think that Paul was illiterate
and dictated all his letters.
Actually, I think we know that for sure
because he says in the preamble to the letters,
I'm Paul,
and this was written down by so-and-so.
But yeah, Hillel and Shammai
had two competing schools of thought,
and Hillel won pretty much every single argument.
And we only remember Shammai as a loser.
We've accepted that we can't know for sure
if Jesus was real or not.
Plenty of people are willing to just say,
yeah, he probably did.
What was Jesus's relationship with Jews?
So to understand that,
we're going to go through
what did Judaism look like in Jesus's day?
So Jesus was around during the second temple.
The first temple was destroyed
many long time ago.
And then the Jews came back to Israel
after some time away,
built a second temple.
And that's where Jesus is going all the time
whenever he goes to Jerusalem.
We have three main factions,
the Sadducees, the Pharisees, and the Zealots.
You might recognize some of these guys
from many of the Jesus stories.
So the Sadducees are the priestly class.
They run the temple.
They're in charge of the temple sacrifices.
They got into power because of a revolt earlier
when they kicked the Greeks out of the temple.
So they kind of have some political status.
And they work together with the Romans
because they have political status.
They want the Romans to not take that away from them.
They're very interested in maintaining the status quo.
The Pharisees are a faction that came out of the exile
in between the first and second temple.
So Judaism was pretty centered around the temple
until the exile when the temple was destroyed.
And they couldn't really do temple stuff anymore.
So they had to figure out,
how do we stay Jews in exile?
So they invented this form of portable Judaism
that was less focused on the temple rituals
and more focused on the Torah,
obeying the commands, personal piety.
This resulted in a decentralization of practice.
We didn't have to necessarily rely on the temple.
And they are a separatist faction
because they're so focused on the law,
they sort of isolate themselves.
They don't hang out with non-Pharisees very much.
They definitely will not eat at the same table as a Gentile
because who knows what Gentiles are eating.
It might not be kosher.
They might be praying to idols at that table, et cetera.
And then the Zealots are the anti-Roman guerrilla fighters.
They lived up in the Judean hill country
and would just get together and go attack some Romans.
Every now and then.
When would this have been?
This would have been around the time of Jesus,
probably around, I think we're talking 20 CE.
The second temple was destroyed in the year 70.
So around 0 to 70-ish CE.
Was there a connection between the Zealots and Masada?
Who?
Masada, the fortification that the Romans took.
I haven't read my Josephus enough, so I'm not...
When you talk about the second temple,
were those described as big temples in Jerusalem?
Is this one like the...
Yes.
Like the golden one?
So the first temple that I refer to is the Temple of Solomon.
It's the central location of Jewish worship
from the time of Solomon
throughout the whole Old Testament, basically.
Solomon is described to have built an enormous temple
with a lot of gold and a lot of stuff.
And then the Babylonians come in and knock that down.
And a while later, the Persians say,
you're allowed to go back and build a new one.
It's not quite as impressive as the first one.
And the people who remember the first one
start crying because it's so lame
compared to what they remember.
And then the Romans knocked that one down,
and now there's no temple.
Okay.
So it's the one temple.
Yes.
One temple.
Okay.
Unless you're a Samaritan
because they had a different temple,
but that's a whole other conversation.
Any other questions?
So this is way before they did the Golden Dome?
Temple?
Yeah, that's a Muslim temple.
The Al-Waksim Mosque.
Yeah.
My bad.
What was Jesus' relationship to all these guys?
We can probably guess that the Pharisees and Sadducees
weren't too fond of him if you've read your Gospels
because they're always trying to trick him
into saying silly things.
So let's start with some stories.
Then they came to Jerusalem,
and he, Jesus, entered the temple
and began to drive out those who were selling
and those who were buying in the temple,
and he overturned the tables of the money changers
and the seats of those who sold doves,
and he would not allow anyone
to carry anything through the temple.
He was teaching and saying,
Is it not written,
My house shall be called a house of prayer
for all the nations?
But you have made it a den of robbers.
And when the chief priests and the scribes heard it,
they kept looking for a way to kill him,
for they were afraid of him,
because the whole crowd was spellbound by his teaching.
It makes sense.
It does make sense.
We're probably talking about the Sadducees here
because it's the temple,
and the Sadducees control the temple cult.
And they are being,
Judy mentioned them earlier today,
saying that they're charging for money conversion.
They're charging for the sacrifices that you have to make.
They're not optional.
They are mandatory.
Everyone's skimming off the top.
And Jesus is not okay with the Sadducees
profiting off of mandatory religious ritual.
So he thinks that everyone should be able to participate
in temple sacrifice,
whether they can afford to or not.
So he comes in and says,
You guys are a bunch of jerks.
I'm flipping your tables.
So there's clearly bad blood between Jesus and the Sadducees.
Next we have Jesus and the Pharisees.
And as Jesus sat at dinner in the house,
many tax collectors and sinners came
and were sitting with Jesus and his disciples.
When the Pharisees saw this,
he said to his disciples,
Why does your teacher eat with tax collectors and sinners?
But when he heard this, he said,
Those who are well have no need of a physician,
but those who are sick.
Go and learn what this means.
I desire mercy, not sacrifice.
For I have not come to call the righteous, but sinners.
So we talked earlier about how Pharisees won't eat with non-Pharisees
because they're worried about becoming ritually impure
or accidentally eating non-kosher food,
food that might have been sacrificed to idols.
So they see Jesus eating with these people,
tax collectors and sinners.
I always think it's funny that tax collectors are lumped in.
The historical reason for that is that tax collectors worked with and for the Romans,
and they usually would not take Jewish law very seriously.
They were pretty assimilated to Roman culture.
They were considered, like, traitors.
Okay, so the Pharisees are very focused on the law,
the book of the law.
But Jesus here is quoting from the prophets, like Isaiah,
in which God says,
Your sacrifices are meaningless to me.
Your festivals are repugnant.
The sacrifice that I want is for you to take care of the poor,
the widow, and the orphan.
Jesus took this message to heart and preached it quite regularly.
And so he's kind of calling the Pharisees out for being very hoity-toity,
but not actually doing anything useful that is actually helping anybody.
We've got quite a few of them people in our society now,
and Jesus needs to come and talk to them again.
That's an understatement.
Yeah.
And we have a story that deals a little bit with his relationship with the zealots.
Then they, meaning the authorities, the Jewish authorities,
sent to him some Pharisees and some Herodians to trap him in what he said.
And they came and said to him,
Teacher, we know that you are sincere and show deference to no one,
for you do not regard people with partiality,
but teach the way of God in accordance with truth.
Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar or not?
Should we pay them or should we not?
But knowing their hypocrisy, he said to them,
Why are you putting me to the test?
Bring me a denarius and let me see it.
And they brought one.
And he said to them,
Whose head is this and whose title?
They answered, Caesar's.
Jesus said to them,
Give to Caesar the things that are Caesar's and to God the things that are God's.
They were utterly amazed at him.
So they're trying to catch him in a trap where if he says,
Yes, we should pay our taxes, then he's a Roman shill.
And if he says, No, we should not pay our taxes,
then they can get him in trouble with the Roman government.
So either way, he's between a rock and a hard place.
But he pulls this maneuver where he says,
Look, it's George Washington's face on the quarter.
God doesn't care about this.
The money is already his.
Just give it back to him.
So he's clearly rejecting the sort of militaristic, anti-Roman position of the Zealots.
What are the Herodians?
Herodians, they're the faction of King Herod,
who was put into power after the Maccabean Revolt,
which was the same revolt that put the Sadducees in power.
So he's pretty much referring to the Sadducees in a roundabout way.
So people higher up.
Yes.
So Jesus had strong words for everybody.
He was very radical,
very interested in reforming the Jewish community into something better.
Are the Jews responsible for killing Jesus?
This has been a thing that Jews have had to deal with for the last 2,000 years,
being called the Christ killers.
According to this book,
Jesus was executed by a crucifixion,
which was a common method of torture and execution used by the Romans.
So the execution of Jesus was a Roman affair,
possibly with the cooperation of Jewish leadership in Jerusalem.
The Romans did not need to try a troublesome Jewish peasant in order to kill him.
They tortured and crucified nameless lower class people all the time in order to get rid of Jesus,
who had caused a disturbance in the temple,
had made radical sounding pronouncements and prophecies,
and was rumored to have aspirations to kingship.
The Romans would have simply taken him by force and crucified him the next day,
along with a few others they were getting rid of.
There was no need for any trial,
much less two or more before different courts
would have been more trouble than a Roman government needed for the desired result.
So the gospel narratives are a little bit confusing
in the context of the actual political reality of the time.
It seems like all the rigmarole was completely unnecessary.
But I like to take literature seriously anyways.
So if we read the gospel accounts and what they say,
we can just say that they happen pretty much
the way that they're written down
and still get some information out of them.
There's a few threads common to all of the gospel accounts.
Some differences, but there are some commonalities.
First one is that in all of the accounts,
Jesus is captured by the Romans in collaboration with the Sadducees
because he is a threat to their power
and the institutions, political institutions that they're a part of.
He is directly flipping over their tables and such
and calling for reform, trying to take away their sources of revenue.
Does anyone know who Barabbas is?
It was the alternative.
Yes.
In the gospel accounts, when Jesus is brought before Pilate,
the governor of Judea,
apparently there is a tradition around Passover
when the governor would pardon one criminal,
whoever the Jews chose.
This is an outrageous tradition.
There's no way this happened.
It's kind of like Prima Nocta and Braveheart,
if you've seen that.
It's very good storytelling,
but it probably didn't happen.
So there's Jesus and there's Barabbas,
who is the other criminal.
He's described as a murderer and a seditionist.
And the Jews say,
we want Barabbas.
Free that guy.
Barabbas is not a real name.
It's Aramaic.
Bar-Abbas, son of the father,
which is completely meaningless.
It basically just means a person.
We can contrast that with the name that Jesus used for himself,
son of man,
which is completely meaningless
and basically just means a person.
So the gospel narratives are creating this dichotomy
between Jesus and Barabbas,
who are their names are meant to be similar,
to call our attention to them.
Jesus is this peace-loving pacifist.
He is submitting himself to execution.
The gospel of John says,
I could free myself if I wanted.
I could have my followers storm this place and free me,
but I'm not going to do that
because my kingdom is a kingdom of peace.
It's a kingdom of the last coming first,
the mighty being brought low.
Meanwhile, Barabbas is an insurrectionist and a murderer.
He's one of the zealots probably
going around trying to gain Jewish independence
from Rome by violent means.
So the story is saying the Jews chose violence
rather than the way of peace that Jesus was teaching.
And I think that's probably the message
that the Jews of the first century would have heard.
So, yeah.
We also know that Jesus was a victim
of sort of a mob mentality
in all of the gospel accounts.
It's the Sadducees who start up
the crucified Jesus chants
and everybody kind of just goes along.
I don't know if anyone here
has seen the movie Borat.
But if you have,
you've seen Sacha Baron Cohen
pretending to be a foreigner
going up and saying things like,
we support your war of terror.
We support killing every single man,
woman, and child in Iraq.
And all the people start cheering
and going along with it.
So it's pretty easy to get a mob
to agree with almost anything.
And again,
Roman execution,
the historicity of whether or not
the Jews were allowed
to administer capital punishment
is in question.
But according to the gospel narratives,
they couldn't,
and that's why they had to bring him
to the Romans.
But pretty clearly,
okay,
so how is Judaism different from Christianity?
Jews are more focused on action than belief.
nobody cares really
if a Jew believes in God or not.
There are a ton of atheist Jews
who are still Jewish
and still very accepted as Jews.
What we care about is
being a good person,
obeying the laws maybe.
Depending on what that means to you,
there are a lot of different positions.
I think for Christians,
mostly there is a lot more
emphasis on belief.
You are expected to believe in Jesus,
believe in the resurrection.
There's a bunch of creeds
like the Apostles' Creed,
the Nicene Creed.
You might know of those.
Many, many Christians
were burned at the stake
by Christian authorities
for having
some heretical beliefs.
Judy would have been
burned at the stake
if she was a believer.
I wouldn't have laughed so long.
That's great.
Christianity is generally considered
to be a pretty individual affair.
It's between you and Jesus.
Judaism is a group activity.
You cannot be Jewish by yourself.
Say what?
It's cultural.
Jews cannot pray alone
most of the prayers.
There's so many people alone.
You're required to pray in dominion,
which is often translated as a quorum,
which is traditionally a group
of ten adult Jewish men.
Today, we will usually let women
be part of the dominion.
Thanks.
You're not allowed to do
morning practices by yourself.
If your mom or dad dies,
you have to pray the morning prayers
in a dominion.
You're not allowed to practice that
in isolation.
So, you have to go to the temple?
Yes.
Yeah.
Currently.
We don't have a temple temple anymore.
So, you'd have to find
like your local synagogue,
which sometimes we will call a temple.
A better translation would be
a house of prayer.
So, yeah.
You can pray at homes
or does it have to be at the synagogue?
It can be anywhere
as long as you have a minion.
Of mostly men.
Depends on how orthodox you are.
Well, that's my question.
So, when you say more focused
on action than belief,
what would an orthodox rabbi say?
Think of that bullet point.
Would they agree with you?
An orthodox is stricter?
Just so I know what you're...
I just want to clarify.
Versus reform.
Right.
There's three major branches of Judaism
today in America.
We have the modern orthodox,
the conservative,
and the reform.
I won't get too much into the history,
but they all have
different positions
about the Jewish law,
and that's the key differentiation.
So, is Jewish law binding?
Are we required
to follow Jewish law?
And, can Jewish law
change over time?
Are we allowed
to reinterpret
the law
in response
to our changing times?
So, the modern orthodox
basically say,
yes, Jewish law is binding,
and no, it does not change.
So, they are very
conservative,
very much sticks in the mud.
The conservative movement
is kind of a middle ground.
Yes, the law is binding.
You have to follow the law,
but we can change it
in response to
our evolving understanding
of humanity
and society.
Reform
are
very loosey-goosey.
The law is not binding.
It's more of a suggestion,
and it's subject to change.
We can adapt it.
So, the modern orthodox
would still agree
that action is much more
important than belief.
But they might think
that a lot of the,
for example,
atheist Jews
are crazy.
So, that would be
under the last cow.
The crazies?
The crazy people.
You're just saying
reform.
Yeah.
They'd probably be
considered more reform,
but I, yeah.
Yes?
Well, I'm focusing
on the word action.
So, when you say
an orthodox
would still believe
that action
is more important
than belief,
what's,
is that action like,
like following
the rituals?
rituals?
Yeah.
For the orthodox,
it would primarily be
doing the three daily prayers,
keeping kosher,
making sure
that you
don't touch
dead bodies
or lizards
or whatever.
But not on good works.
Not so much
for the orthodox,
but the further
you get
to the right
of this chart,
the less
that they're worried
about the sort
of traditional
laws
and the more
that they're worried
about the more
social justice
part of it,
the prophetic,
I don't care
about your fasts,
help the poor.
Clothing,
clothing
and hair.
Yeah,
that's more on this side,
the clothing requirements.
This just is reminding me
of Christianity today
with the extreme
conservative fundamentalists
who would have
stormed out of here
when you said
anything at all
about whether
Jesus existed
or not
because the Bible
is inerrant,
infallible
and has no
contradictions in it.
I mean,
that's their position
and so the law
is everything
and your belief
is everything.
But on the other side,
it would be like
the UCC for sure
and the Presbyterians
to a degree
that we're going
to put social justice
and human needs first.
So would you say
we're more reform?
Sure.
As Christians,
oh yeah,
because the folks
on the left,
on this chart that is,
don't even think
that progressive Christians
are Christians at all.
They think we're going to hell
because we don't believe
the way they believe.
They're very rigid
and that's who's
in power right now.
That mindset
is the powerful mindset
in our country.
In fact,
the modern orthodox
wouldn't even consider me Jewish
because I had
conservative conversion
and that is not
strict enough for them.
Bless you.
So are there different
synagogues
with these different,
you can be a
conservative
synagogue
or you can be a reform.
For the most part,
a Jew is a Jew
and you can go
to wherever you want.
This is
more at
like an institutional level
of,
you know,
there's like a bunch
of rabbis
in a building somewhere
making rules
and publishing books
and stuff
but most everyday Jews
just don't really care
that much
and will go to
whatever synagogue
is closest.
So if you
walk
to synagogue,
does that mean
you're at least
a conservative?
Would the reformed Jews
consider that
this idea
of not doing
work,
not starting
your car,
would they go
for that
or is that
a conservative Jew?
The car issue
is not really
a work issue.
It's about
kindling fire
on the Sabbath
or carrying
which are two
other prohibitions
that you're not
allowed to do
those things
on the Sabbath.
Modern Orthodox,
you definitely
are not allowed
to drive a car.
The leaders
of the conservative
movement
made a ruling
some years ago
that
it's better
for you
to go
to synagogue
than not.
So if you
must drive
to get to
synagogue
then you can
but you probably
shouldn't be
driving anywhere else.
That kind of
sounds like
an Amish people.
So with not
using the power,
the energy
that is only
on Sabbath.
Electric cars
are fine.
Really?
Because
it's kindling
fire that
is prohibited.
So the spark
flag
or the...
Yeah,
internal combustion
engines are all...
But without using
lights in the house,
isn't that considered
by the Orthodox...
Modern Orthodox,
for some reason,
have decided
that electricity
is fire.
Yes.
Nobody else
agrees.
Okay.
Weird.
Yeah.
So you can go back
to what you were saying.
I don't know
what I was saying.
What was I saying?
Alright,
so traditionally
Judaism is transmitted
by the mother.
So if your mom
is Jewish
then you're
automatically Jewish.
Different positions
on this now.
Most people
will say that
if either of your
parents was Jewish
and you were
exposed to Judaism
growing up
then you count.
Converting to...
Yes.
Can I ask a question?
Okay,
so my grandfather
was Jewish
and my grandmother
wasn't.
Mm-hmm.
Does that affect
my grandfather's
Judaism
or...
Is the question
does marrying
a non-Jew
make him less Jewish?
Does he...
He stays Jewish,
right?
Yes.
Okay.
You know,
you can't stop
being Jewish.
Okay.
You couldn't
convert to another
religion?
I could,
but I wouldn't
stop being a Jew.
I would just be
an apostate.
A non-Jew
not a person
or an apostate?
Is that a Christian
or Christian Jews
or some Christian Jews?
Yeah,
there are.
Yeah.
There are a lot
of Buddhist Jews.
A whole lot
We call them
Jubus.
Oh!
But don't repeat
that.
That's our word.
So,
converting to Judaism
is quite different
than Christianity.
Especially,
for some reason,
like,
the more conservative
Christian,
the easier it is
to become Christian.
like,
you just pray
the prayer,
like,
I accept Jesus
into my heart
and boom,
you're Christian.
For Judaism,
if anybody remembers
the,
what is it called,
confirmation classes,
that kind of stuff,
it's sort of like that.
We generally have to spend
at least a year
studying Judaism,
learning all the
laws and the
traditions
and the practices
and the customs
and the history.
So it's more like
trying to get
citizenship
in a new country
where you have to
live in the country
for a while
and then you have
to take an exam.
When I converted,
I had to sit
in front of a
Jewish court
of three rabbis
and they asked me
questions
and I had to
prove that I knew
what I was talking about
and I'm sincere.
before I was alive.
Yeah.
Oh, there was a lot
of pressure.
I dabbed like an idiot.
Without being a smart
aleck, right?
I was still a smart aleck.
Do you read Hebrew?
Is that a requirement?
Reading Hebrew
is a requirement
for the modern Orthodox.
I cannot read Hebrew.
I can sort of
sound things out
a little bit
but a lot of the letters
look the same
and the vowels
are really hard
to figure out.
But that's the end
of my slides.
Okay, there.
That was perfect.
That's very nice.
Very good.
Thank you.
Yeah.
That was interesting.
I missed a lot of it.
Thank you.
Yay.
Next time,
I think I will
focus more
on some of the
common Jewish practices
like what is
Jewish prayer like?
What's the deal
with the funny hats
and the clothes
and stuff?
Oh, yeah.
That kind of thing.
Mm-hmm.
So...
Thank you.